Guide to the John Howard Griffin Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series VIII: Black Like Me
  - Science Digest To John Howard Griffin, New York, 10 June 1969, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 7, Folder 244)
  - Sherman, Frank To John Howard Griffin, Long Island, NY, 12 Jan.1962, (3 page t.l.s.) (Box 7, Folder 245)
  - Sibert, Rod To Elizabeth Griffin-Bonazzi, [Columbia, MD], 9 May 1989, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 7, Folder 246)
    [With reply
  - SAGA To John Howard Griffin, New York, 12 July 1963, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 7, Folder 247)
  - Talking Tapes To Houghton Mifflin, St. Louis, MO, 1 November 1967, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 7, Folder 248)
  - Correspondence regarding translations of Black Like Me into Japanese, Polish, etc., [v.p.], 1962-1984, (ca. 11 letters) (Box 7, Folder 249)
  - University of Chicago Press To John Howard Griffin, Chicago, 1 December 1965, (1 t.d. (mimeograph) (Box 7, Folder 250)
  - Xerox Education Division To John Howard Griffin, New York, 23 January 1968, (1 t.l.s. (copy) (Box 7, Folder 251)
  - Spokane Public Library Reading list, Washington, [n.d.], (1 pamphlet) (Box 7, Folder 252)
  - Hernandez-Senter, Juan This single-spaced typescript (a photocopy) is the first Spanish translation of Black Like Me, [n.p.], 1992, (156 page t.ms. (photocopy) (Box 7, Folder 253)
    [The translation was made by Dr. Juan Hernandez-Senter, at the invitation of the Griffin Estate, in 1989. This authorized translation has not been published. Translated from the New American Library Penguin paperback edition, it does not include that Signet edition's "Epilogue," which will be added, along with an introduction, if the translation is published.
  - Uncorrected proof copy of Black Like Me, Houghton Mifflin: Boston, 1961, (1 volume) (Box 7, Folder 254)
  - Paperback copy of Black Like Me, Signet: New York, 1996, (1 volume) (Box 7, Folder 255)
    [Inscribed by Elizabeth and Robert Bonazzi, 31 March 1997
- Series IX: Personal Essays and Journalism
  By examining these typescripts in relation to the published pieces--both the Dialogue and the Journal article--we get a close look at Griffin's method. The Correspondence from this period--between Griffin and Fr. Thompson; between Griffin and Ramparts editor/publisher Ed Keating; between Griffin and Bishop Greco (Fr Thompson's superior); as well as the correspondences of the priest and the bishop (and both of these men with Keating of Ramparts)--document an interesting struggle that all experienced. Bishop Greco tried to block the interview on the grounds that Fr. Thompson's documented experience of racism by the Church would not be good for the Church. Eventually, the interview ran, setting off a controversy that reached beyond Bishop Greco's diocese to the hierarchy of the Catholic Church in the US during the 1960s.
  - "Beyond Black Like Me", Mansfield, TX, [n.d.], (18 pages t.ms. (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 256)
    [Intended for The Saturday Evening Post, but never published
  - "On Our Doorstep", Pio Decimo Press: St. Louis, [n.d.], (27 page photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 257)
  - "Some Afterthoughts On Black Like Me", Mansfield, TX, 1962, (12 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 258)
    [Published in Texas Observer under the title "The Shine Boy Has His Dream"
  - ["Martin Luther King's Moment], [Mansfield, TX], [1963], (3 pages a.ms., 2 pages t.ms., 3 pages t.ms. (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 259)
  - "Martin Luther King's Moment", Sign, April 1963, (6 page photocopy of article) (Box 8, Folder 260)
  - Review of Crisis in Black and White, by Charles E. Silberman, [Mansfield, TX], [1964], (3 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 261)
    [With a photocopy of the published review in The Saturday Review
  - "The Intrinsic Other", [n.p.], [1967], (2 page photocopy, 9 page photocopy (German) (Box 8, Folder 262)
  - "Racist Sins of Christians", Sign: Union City, NJ, 1963, (12 page pamphlet, 11 page photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 263)
  - Interview with Father August Thompson, [n.p.], [n.d.], (17 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 264)
  - Interview with Father August Thompson, [n.p.], [n.d.], (9 page t.ms. (carbon, early draft) (Box 8, Folder 265)
  - Journal notes re. his interview with Father Thompson and its aftermath, [n.p.], December 1964 - January l966, (14 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 266)
  - "The Negro & The White Conscience", Ramparts, December 1963 (Box 8, Folder 267)
    [The published version of his interview with Father A. Thompson
  - "Journal of A Trip South", Ramparts, December 1963, (7 page photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 268)
  - "Anatomy of a Bigot", [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 269)
  - "Are We on the Verge of Interracial War?", Mansfield, TX, [n.d.], (11 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 270)
  - Preface to From. Corps to CORE, by Father John P. Markoe, Fort Worth, TX, [n.d.], (7 pages t.ms. (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 271)
    [With photocopy of a review of the book by Katherine Court
  - "Speech by John Howard Griffin", The University of Iowa, 3-5 February 1969, (46 page t.ms. (photocopy, with ms. corrections) (Box 8, Folder 272)
    [Became both a monograph published by the University of Iowa and a text on microfiche at Columbia University--entitled "Racial Equality: Myth and Reality"
  - "The Tip-Off", Ramparts, [n.d.], (3 page photocopy (plus Griffin's postscript) (Box 8, Folder 273)
  - Lecture notes: Racism, [n.p.], [n.d.], (28 pages t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 274)
  - Lecture Notes: Racism, [n.p.], 1964, (6 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 275)
  - Lecture Notes: Racism, [n.p.], [n.d.], (4 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 276)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Again, Lillian Smith" [Review of Killers of the Dream, by Lillian Smith], Southwest Review, Winter 1962, (2 page Offprint) (Box 8, Folder 277)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Color Line on the Front Lines": Review of And Then We Heard the Thunder, by John Oliver Killens, Saturday Review, 26 January 1963, (3 page photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 278)
  - Griffin, John Howard "On Either Side of Violence": Review of books by Daisy Bates and Sarah Patton Boyle, Saturday Review, 27 October 1962, (1 page photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 279)
  - Griffin, John Howard Statement on Racism, The Critic, June/July 1964, (3 page photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 280)
  - "Terror in Mexico", Michoacan, Mexico, 17 April 1961, (32 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 281 & 282)
  - "The Watch of the Dead", [n.p.], [n.d.], (7 page t.ms. (with ms. corrections) (Box 8, Folder 283)
  - "The Tarascans of Michoacan", Mansfield, TX, [n.d.], (4 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 284)
    [Published in the booklet The Singing Boys of Mexico
  - Cultivated Mind - Guardian Genius of Democracy, University of Dallas: Irving, TX, 1961, (22 page proofs (with ms. corrections) (Box 8, Folder 285)
  - "Publish or Perish", Mexico, 1965, (18 page t.ms. (carbon, with ms. corrections), 1 t.l.s. (from Owens to Griffin) (Box 8, Folder 286)
    [Article by Griffin and Professor Robert T. Owens; intended for Ramparts, but unpublished.
  - Review of Constraint by Copyright, by M.S. Schnapper, Mansfield, TX, [1960], (3 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 287)
    [For Teachers College Record
  - The Little Brothers, Ramparts, May 1965, (7 page photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 288)
  - "The Passion of Georges Rouault" Photocopy of catalog introduction by Robert de Bolli and translated from the French by Griffin, Valley House Gallery, Dallas, TX, 1962, (12 page photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 289)
  - Mercadier, Fernand To John Howard Griffin, Algeria & France, July 1960 & February 1953, (2 t.l.s. 1 annotated calling card (with griffin's Carbon replies) (Box 8, Folder 290)
  - "Desert Slaves" by Fernand Mercadier. Translated from the French by John Howard Griffin, Mansfield, TX, [n.d.], (ca. 55 pages t.ms. (with ms. corrections) (Box 8, Folder 291 & 292)
  - Review of Warriors of God, by Walter Nigg, Dallas Times-Herald, April 1959, (1 page photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 293)
  - "Notes on Censorship", [n.p.], [n.d.], (7 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 294)
  - "Notes on Current Censorship", [n.p.], [n.d.], (11 page t.ms.) (Box 9, Folder 295)
  - Correspondence re. censorship in Texas, Mansfield, TX, 18 Sept. 1961 & 20 Feb. 1962, (3 page t.l. (carbon), 1 page t.l. (carbon) (Box 9, Folder 296)
  - "Censorship, Literature and Juvenile Corruption", Mansfield, TX, [n.d.], (14 page t.ms. (carbon, with ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 297)
    [Published title "The Prude and the Lewd"
  - "Preface to L'Opera Noir", Mansfield, TX, 7 August 1963, (10 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 9, Folder 298)
    [With autograph postcard from Gabriel Cousin, 1965
  - [The Poulenc Behind the Mask], Mansfield, TX, (10 t.ms. (first draft), 8 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 9, Folder 299)
    [Published in Ramparts
  - "Arthur Louri: A Great Composer Rediscovered", Ramparts, 1965, (13 page photocopy) (Box 9, Folder 300)
  - "The Men from the Boys" [Essay on writing published in Basilian Teacher], [n.p.], [n.d.], (8 page photocopy) (Box 9, Folder 301)
  - "Gerhart Munch - The Exception to the Rule", [n.p.], [n.d.], (4 page t.ms. (with ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 302)
  - Luis Berb r & The Singing Boys of Mexico, [n.p.], [n.d.], (19 page photocopy) (Box 9, Folder 303)
  - Griffin, John Howard To Arthur Louri Mansfield, TX, 29 June & 20 Dec. 1962, (2 t.l.s. (carbons) (Box 9, Folder 304)
  - "Arthur Louri: A Great Composer Rediscovered", [n.p.], [ca. 1964], (8 page t.ms. (with ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 305)
  - Valley House Gallery To John Howard Griffin, Dallas, TX, 31 July 1962, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 9, Folder 306)
    [With copies of 4 Griffin letters re. Rouault's Passion series
- Series X: The Church and the Black Man
  - The Church and the Black Man, Pflaum Press: Dayton, OH, 1969, (109 page t.ms. (copy, with ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 307; 319-321)
    [Griffin's follow-up book to Black Like Me
  - Ahmann, Mathew "The Church and the Urban White", [n.p.], [n.d.], (16 page t.ms. (copy, with ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 308)
    [Epilogue I to The Church and the Black Man
  - Black Priests' Caucus "The Position of the Catholic Church in the Black Community", [n.p.], January 1969, (14 page t.ms. (copy, with ms. annotations) (Box 9, Folder 309)
    [Epilogue II to The Church and the Black Man
  - John J. McHale To John Howard Griffin, Pflaum Publishers: Dayton, OH, 7 Nov. 1966 - 10 Oct. 1969, (11 t.l.s.) (Box 9, Folder 310)
    [With a press release and memo re. publicity program for the book
  - Correspondence regarding the French edition: Original Typescripts of Letters by Rosica Colin, Griffin's foreign agent (3 Letters) Typescript carbon of Griffin letter to agent Original Typescripts of 3 Letters from Pflaum editor (Box 9, Folder 311)
  - Permissions letters regarding materials quoted in the book (Box 9, Folder 312)
  - Rev Emanueli Clarizio, Apostolic Delegate of Canada To John Howard Griffin, Ottawa, 29 April 1969, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 9, Folder 313)
    [With carbon of Griffin's t.l. to Clarizio
  - William O. Broderick To John Howard Griffin, Department of State, Washington, D.C., 27 July 1970, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 9, Folder 314)
    [Broderick, Director of Caribbean Affairs, had published a study about urban problems that was circulated to federal and Catholic organizations, as well as to such individuals as Griffin, whose Black Like Me and The Church and the Black Man Broderick greatly admired
  - R. Fentener van Vlissingen To John Howard Griffin, Rotterdam, 1 April 1970 (Box 9, Folder 315)
    [Dutch psychiatrist, about The Church and the Black Man; letters from Thomas Merton; and Griffin's work on the Merton biography.
  - Bishop Harold Perry To John Howard Griffin, New Orleans, 28 November 1969, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 9, Folder 316)
    [Thanking Griffin for a copy of The Church and the Black Man, which the Bishop calls an "open, frank and dynamic treatment of the weak points and the strong points of our apostolate to integrate the Black Man into the main stream of Catholic living is excellently presented and should be productive of good results."
  - Paul Hilsdale To John Howard Griffin, Los Angeles, 7 June 1964, (2 page t.l.) (Box 9, Folder 317)
  - Ralph Goman To Marian B. De Lollis, Union City, NJ, 14 July 1966, (1 page t.l.s. (copy) (Box 9, Folder 318)
    [Regarding the use of Griffin's article, "The Racist Sins of Christians".
- Series XI.Scattered Shadows and The John Howard Griffin Reader
  The Reader, published by Houghton Mifflin in 1968, was a 600 page cloth edition of Griffin's best work to that time; the collection sold 40,000 copies, but was never reissued in a paperback edition. The Reader included condensed versions of his two published novels--The Devil Rides Outside and Nuni; ample selections from two other published books--Land of the Hiqh Sky, a history of the staked plains region of west Texas, and Black Like Me. Three other sections completed the volume: a section of his photographic portraits, a gathering of journalistic pieces on racism, and a selection of "works-in-progress" that included two chapters from Scattered Shadows. The Reader was edited by Bradford Daniel, who also condensed the two novels and introduced each portion of the collection. The volume also contained an essay on Griffin's work by literary historian Maxwell Geismar, and several excerpts from Griffin's journals.. This series contains Griffin's correspondence with both Daniel and editors at Houghton Mifflin, and photocopies of the front matter to the book. There are no working manuscripts as everything was gathered from mostly published sources, and all selecting and editing were carried out by Daniel, who was Griffin's secretary at that time. (Copies of published reviews are included.. While The Reader was being readied for publication, Griffin was still lecturing on racism full-time, in order both to fulfill what he considered his obligation (under spiritual direction) to the civil rights struggle, and to support his wife and four children.. Besides the lecture circuit and writing magazine pieces on racism, Griffin worked on the manuscript of Scattered Shadows whenever possible.. Scattered Shadows, the autobiography of his loss of sight, decade of blindness, and eventual sight-recovery, has never been published as a book. The first 11 of 20 chapters were completed for Houghton Mifflin in 1967 and a contract was issued. However, Griffin never revised the last 9 chapters (which would have come from his ongoing journals) because the events of 1968 forced him back on the lecture circuit and also to the trouble spots of racial strife.. He never returned to the autobiography even after the explosions of 1968 had passed because; near the end of that year his friend and colleague, Thomas Merton, died of accidental electrocution in Bangkok (on December 10).. After negotiations with other publishers, Griffin and Houghton Mifflin agreed on a contract for the production of a photographic book (including Merton's photographs and drawings and Griffin's portraits of the monk and photographs of the Abbey of Gethsemani and its spacious grounds, along with texts by Griffin). The project eventually became A Hidden Wholeness: The Visual World of Thomas Merton, published by Houghton 1970. Early on in the process of making this visual book, Griffin interacted with the three members of the Merton Legacy Trust. By spring of 1969, the Trust decided to offer the "Official Biography" to Griffin. At first, he declined; later, he accepted the invitation, hoping that this new large work would support his family and allow him to withdraw from the lecture circuit and write full-time. Considering how difficult lecturing had became due to various medical set-backs and resolving any guilt he might have felt for not continuing the civil rights struggle, he leaped into the project with enthusiasm.. Griffin hoped that Scattered Shadows would be published after the Merton biography--both by Houghton-Mifflin. However, researching the biography took several more years than he had anticipated--partly because the subject was so complex and far-reaching and partly due to his own declining health--and there was never time to return to the autobiography.. The two chapters that appear in The Reader were first published in Ramparts magazine. In fact, the chapters appeared twice in that Catholic periodical--first, in 1963, when Ramparts was a quarterly with limited circulation, and then again, in 1966, when it had become a widely-read monthly. A third chapter, entitled "My Friend, Reverdy" in The Reader, first appeared in Southwest Review, the SMU literary quarterly. Various other pieces from the manuscript were published in such Catholic magazines as Jubilee and Catholic World; and an account of his recovery of sight was published in Readers Digest and in the anthology The Spirit of Man.. This series contains a photocopy of the Ramparts chapters published in that magazine, as well as 20 file folders containing typescript carbons of the first 11 chapters from the unfinished manuscript. (Also six of Griffin's original file folders with typed labels made by the author.). These various chapter drafts afford glimpses of Griffin's manner of line by line revision and section by section reorganization--especially when compared to the few chapters that were published.
  - Chapter One. First Draft., Mansfield, TX, [n.d.], (40 pages t.ms. (carbon, with the author's and editors ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 322)
  - Chapter One: Second draft, Mansfield, TX, [n.d.], (22 pages t.ms. (carbon, with ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 323)
  - Chapter One: Third draft, Mansfield, TX, [n.d.], (22 pages t.ms. (carbon, with ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 324)
  - Chapter Two:- First draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (15 pages t.ms. (carbon, with Griffin's handwritten revisions in ink) (Box 9, Folder 325)
  - Chapter Two: Second draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (18 page t.ms. (carbon, with ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 326)
  - Chapter Two: Final version, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (16 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 9, Folder 327)
  - Chapter Three: First draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (16 pages t.ms. (carbon, with Griffin's ms. revisions) (Box 9, Folder 328)
    [Incomplete missing pp. 43-47
  - Chapter Three: Second draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (22 pages t.ms. (carbon) (Box 9, Folder 329)
  - Chapter Three: Final draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (18 pages t.ms. (carbon) (Box 9, Folder 330)
  - Chapter Four: First draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (38 pages t.ms. (carbon, with Griffin's ms. corrections) (Box 9, Folder 331)
  - Chapter Four: Second draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (30 pages t.ms. (carbon) (Box 9, Folder 332)
  - Chapter Four: Third draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (29 pages t.ms. (carbon) (Box 9, Folder 333)
  - Chapter Four: Third draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (29 pages t.ms. (carbon) (Box 9, Folder 333)
  - Chapter Five: First draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (24 pages t.ms. (carbon, with Griffin's ms. corrections) (Box 10, Folder 334)
  - Chapter Five: Second draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (16 pages t.ms. (carbon & photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 335)
  - Chapter Six: Final draft, [Mansfield, TX], 11 October 1967, (12 pages t.ms. (carbon & photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 336)
  - Chapter Seven: Three drafts in typescript carbon, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (4 page t.ms. (carbon), 4 page t.ms. (carbon), 5 page t.ms (carbon, "10/11/67") (Box 10, Folder 337)
  - Chapter Eight: Three drafts, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (10 page t.ms. (carbon, with Griffin's ms. corrections), 12 page t.ms. (carbon, "Superceded"), 8 page t.ms. ("Final carbon", "10/12/67") (Box 10, Folder 338)
  - Chapter Nine: First draft & Final version, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (17 page t.ms. (carbon, with ms. corrections, "Superceded"), 22 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 10, Folder 339)
  - Chapter Ten: First and Second drafts, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (pages t.ms. (carbon, with Griffin's ms. corrections), pages t.ms. (carbon) (Box 10, Folder 340 & 341)
  - Chapter Eleven: First draft, [Mansfield, TX], [n.d.], (28 page t.ms. (carbon, with ms. corrections) (Box 10, Folder 342)
  - Scattered Shadows, Ramparts, January 1966, (13 page photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 342A)
  - The John Howard Griffin Reader, Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1968, (7 page photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 243)
  - Houghton, Mifflin To John Howard Griffin, Boston, 30 June 1965 - 21 February 1967, (10 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related material) (Box 10, Folder 344)
    [Re. The Reader
  - Daniel, Bradford To John Howard Griffin, Fort Worth, TX, 17 Aug.1965 & 8 Sept. 1973, (2 t.l.s. (with relater carbon letter) (Box 10, Folder 345)
  - The John Howard Griffin Reader Notes & Photographs, Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1968, (9 page photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 346)
  - The John Howard Griffin Reader Reviews, Wall Street Journal; Washington Star; The Dallas Morning News, 1968, (3 page photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 347)
- Series XII. The Decade of the Sixties
  This Series is the second largest in the Griffin Archives. It gathers all the correspondence, documents and marginalia. from that decade.
  - Sunseries XII.1: General
    - Passport and personal effects document for several trips to Europe, [n.p.], 1964, (3 page photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 348)
    - The Royal Photographic Society of Great Britain To John Howard Griffin, London, 29 July 1965, (1 page t.l.s., 1 t.l., 1 member's card, 1 brochure) (Box 10, Folder 349)
    - Kennedy, Robert To John Howard Griffin, Washington, DC, 20 June 1966, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 10, Folder 350)
      [Re. the visit of Father Dominique Pire
    - Kennedy, Edward To John Howard Griffin, Washington, DC, 29 March 1968, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 10, Folder 351)
      [Re. revision of the copyright law
    - J. Frank Dobie To John Howard Griffin, Austin, TX, 2 January 1962, (1 page t.l.s. (with carbon reply and clipping) (Box 10, Folder 352)
    - Griffin, John Howard To Roland Hayes, [n.p.], 8 April 1969, (1 page t.l.s. (carbon), 1 article (photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 353)
    - Bok, Curtis To John Howard Griffin, Supreme Court, PA, 17 October 1961, (1 page t.l.s. (with carbon reply) (Box 10, Folder 354)
    - Mays, Benjamin To John Howard Griffin, Morehouse College, Atlanta, 8 Feb. 1962, (1 page t.l.s. (with carbon reply) (Box 10, Folder 355)
    - Alinsky, Saul D. To John Howard Griffin, Industrial Areas Foundation of Chicago, 3 June 1966, (1 page t.l.s. (with related material) (Box 10, Folder 356)
    - Griffin, John Howard To Roy Wilkins, Mansfield, TX, 28 January 1965, (1 page t.l.s. (carbon) (Box 10, Folder 357)
    - Griffin, John Howard To Cardinal Richard Cushing, Mansfield, TX, 11 August 1964, (1 page t.l.s. (carbon) (Box 10, Folder 358)
    - Chaney, Fannie Lee To John Howard Griffin, [Meridian, Mississippi], 30 Nov. 1964 - 15 March 1965, (3 t.p.c.s.) (Box 10, Folder 359)
      [Mother of James Chaney, the black civil rights worker murdered (with Schwerner and Goodman) in Mississippi.
    - Clyde Kennard; also one typescript page of notes on Kennard's mother, Mrs. Leona Smith; as well as one page of autograph notes by Griffin. Mansfield, TX, [n.d.] & 1, 13 April 1963, (1 page a.ms., 1 page t.ms., 3 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 10, Folder 360)
      [Griffin considered Clyde Kennard to be one of the most courageous Christians he ever knew. Kennard was a Mississippi black man falsely accused of a petty crime because he tried to enter the state University, only to be given an outrageously stiff jail term at hard labor.
    - Smith, Leonia To John Howard Griffin, Hattiesburg, MS, 1 Dec. 1964 - 19 June 1967, (5 a.l.s., 1 t.p.c. (with related material) (Box 10, Folder 361)
    - Silver, Dr. James W. To John Howard Griffin, MI, 11 June 1963, (1 page t.l.s. (with carbon reply) (Box 10, Folder 362)
    - Drummond, Dwight L. To John Howard Griffin, University of Michigan, 16 April 1962- 12 April 1966, (16 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s. (with related material) (Box 10, Folder 363)